Guide to the Sheffield Scientific School, Yale University, Class Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Sheffield Scientific School, Yale University, class records
1873-1974
RU 1084
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.58
(4 envelopes and 1 box)
The materials consist of correspondence, photographs and printed ephemera documenting the Sheffield Scientific School Classes of 1912 and 1904.
Yale University. Sheffield Scientific School
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 10-B (YRG 10-B), Records of Sheffield Scientific School classes.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials were transferred from Sheffield Scientific School, 2008. Gift of Richard J. Mammana, Jr., 2012-2013. Gift of Professor J. Gary Lutz, 2016. Transfer from the Office of the President, 2018.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
In 1847, Yale established the Department of Philosophy and Arts, which offered courses in philosophy, the arts, and the sciences. As the scientific fields gained in strength, the School of Applied Chemistry and the School of Engineering were developed. These schools were combined in 1854 to form the Yale Scientific School. In 1858 Joseph Earl Sheffield purchased the old Medical Institution and presented it to Yale, along with scientific apparatus and an endowment. The new school, dedicated as the Sheffield Scientific School, in 1861 became one of the first schools of higher education in the United States to devote its curriculum specifically to scientific training. The faculty conducted graduate as well as undergraduate courses in the sciences and engineering until 1919 when the former were discontinued. In 1954 graduate level courses were reinstated. The School's functions were absorbed by the Graduate School in 1956.
Scope and Contents
The materials consist of correspondence, photographs and printed ephemera documenting the Sheffield Scientific School Classes of 1912 and 1904.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by accession.
Class reunions; Photographs; Yale University -- Alumni and alumnae; Yale University. Sheffield Scientific School; Yale University. Sheffield Scientific School. Class of 1912
- Class of 1912, Sheffield Scientific School, memorabilia, 1908-1912; Accession 2009-A-173; .02 linear feet
  Conditions Governing Access
  The materials are open for research.
  Scope and Contents
  The records consist of photographs and printed ephemera documenting the Sheffield Scientific School Class of 1912.
  - Photographs and printed ephemera, 1908-1912 (Box 1)
- Class of 1904, Sheffield Scientific School, correspondence and memorabilia, Accession 2012-A-074
  The 2012-A-074 accession contains correspondence primarily from Jules R. Breuchaud, Secretary-Treasurer, to Thomas Newton Rae, members of the Sheffield Scientific School Class of 1904. Also included are a small snapshot and materials related to the St. Elmo Society.
  - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1967-1974 (Box 1)
- Class of 1904, Sheffield Scientific School, correspondence and photograph, 1959-1966; Accession 2014-A-003
  - Correspondence and photograph, 1959-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Class of 1873, Sheffield Scientific School, statistics booklet, Accession 2017-A-051
  - Statistics booklet, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Scrapbook of Stanley Worthington Dwinnell, Class of 1912s, 1908-1912; Accession 2018-A-0068
  - Scrapbook, 1908-1912 (Box 1, Folder 1)